<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>os on jpnt&#39;s website</title>
    <link>https://jpnt.github.io/tags/os/</link>
    <description>Recent content in os on jpnt&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© João Pinto</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 23:21:40 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jpnt.github.io/tags/os/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Steam on Void Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/voidlinux-steam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 23:21:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/voidlinux-steam/</guid>
      <description>How to install Steam on Void Linux 1. Non-free repositories To install Steam, you will need to enable the non-free repositories. To do so, install the non-free repository packages:
# xbps-install -S void-repo-nonfree void-repo-multilib-nonfree 2. Install Steam Now, you should have the Steam package available. To install it:
# xbps-install -S steam 3. Additional packages Unlike the Arch Linux steam package, in Void Linux this package does not contain the additional library packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LEARN LINUX THE RIGHT WAY</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/learn-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 22:41:20 -0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/learn-linux/</guid>
      <description>WHAT IS LINUX? Concept of a kernel Hardware &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Kernel &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Software Monolithic kernel vs Microkernel Open source nature Worldwide development You can contribute to it WHAT IS A LINUX DISTRIBUTION OS based on monolithic Linux kernel WHAT MAKES A LINUX DISTRIBUTION Core: libc; Base: coreutils; Extras; Most Linux distros differ on Extras DIFFERENCE BETWEEN LINUX DISTROS User-friendly vs user-centric distros Rolling release vs fixed release Linux Mint vs Arch Binary vs Source based INSTALLING SOFTWARE ON A LINUX DISTRO A linux distro distributes packages Package manager: apt, pacman ´apt install firefox´ ´pacman -S firefox´ FLEXIBILITY OF LINUX Used on super computers 100% of top 500 Used on the server 96% of top 1,000,000 Used on personal computers INTRODUCTION TO THE TERMINAL Commands are programs ls, cd, cat, pwd, whoami, echo, ps Learn every command: ´man command´ Everything is a file Programs, devices and drivers are files ´ls /dev´, ´ls /bin´ AUTOMATION AND SCRIPTING Bash scripts Shell vs Terminal Variables: PATH, export, env ´#!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Save Battery on Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/battery-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 18:52:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/battery-linux/</guid>
      <description>Linux on laptops The downside of Linux when it comes to laptops is that it&amp;rsquo;s very power hungry, however we can fix this by installing a power saving program called auto-cpufreq.
How to install auto-cpufreq There are many ways of installing auto-cpufreq provided at https://github.com/AdnanHodzic/auto-cpufreq.
However, I will install it from source code, since this way will work on most Linux distributions.
Clone the git repository: $ git clone https://github.com/AdnanHodzic/auto-cpufreq.git Change the directory to the repository and execute the installer: $ cd auto-cpufreq &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pop!_OS Install</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/popos-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 19:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/popos-install/</guid>
      <description>Pop!_OS is a free and open-source Linux distribution, based on Ubuntu, and it uses the GNOME desktop.
It provides full support for AMD and Nvidia graphics cards out-of-the-box, which makes it an excellent choice for beginners.
Download Pop!_OS Go to https://pop.system76.com/ and click on download.
Pop!_OS comes in two versions: the latest, and the LTS (Long Term Support). I will choose the latest, since I want to use the latest features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disable Suspend on Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/disable-suspend/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 13:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/disable-suspend/</guid>
      <description>Disable / Mask services using systemctl sudo systemctl mask sleep.target suspend.target hibernate.target hybrid-sleep.target Edit &amp;ldquo;/etc/systemd/logind.conf&amp;rdquo; to avoid errors and high CPU usage HandleSuspendKey=ignore HandleHibernateKey=ignore HandleLidSwitch=ignore HandleLidSwitchExternalPower=ignore HandleLidSwitchDocked=ignore Restart systemd-logind sudo systemctl restart systemd-logind Check for errors journalctl -xe That&amp;rsquo;s it!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
