<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on jpnt&#39;s website</title>
    <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on jpnt&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© João Pinto</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 21:02:39 -0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jpnt.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Modern Software is a disaster</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/modern-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 21:02:39 -0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/modern-software/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Designing simple and elegant software is far more difficult than letting ad-hoc or over-ambitious features obscure the code over time.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; suckless.org
We live in a really agitated world where information flows much faster than anyone could ever grasp. Due to the agile technological advancements and the appearance of new technologies every day, the demand for people on the Information Technology sector is extremely high.
However, because there is still so much software to write, there is no market pressure in the software space to ship high quality code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LEARN LINUX THE RIGHT WAY</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/learn-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 22:41:20 -0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/learn-linux/</guid>
      <description>WHAT IS LINUX?  Concept of a kernel  Hardware &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Kernel &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Software Monolithic kernel vs Microkernel   Open source nature  Worldwide development You can contribute to it    WHAT IS A LINUX DISTRIBUTION  OS based on monolithic Linux kernel  WHAT MAKES A LINUX DISTRIBUTION  Core: libc; Base: coreutils; Extras;  Most Linux distros differ on Extras    DIFFERENCE BETWEEM LINUX DISTROS  User-friendly vs user-centric distros Rolling release vs fixed release  Linux Mint vs Arch   Binary vs Source based  INSTALLING SOFTWARE ON A LINUX DISTRO  A linux distro distributes packages Package manager: apt, pacman  apt install firefox pacman -S firefox    FLEXIBILITY OF LINUX  Used on super computers  100% of top 500   Used on the server  96% of top 1,000,000   Used on personal computers  INSTRODUCTION TO THE TERMINAL  Commands are programs  ls, cd, cat, pwd, whoami, echo, ps Learn every command: man &amp;lt;command&amp;gt;   Everything is a file  Programs, devices and drivers are files ls /dev, ls /bin    AUTOMATION AND SCRIPTING  Bash scripts  Shell vs Terminal Variables: PATH, export, env #!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Save Battery on Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/battery-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 18:52:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/battery-linux/</guid>
      <description>Linux on laptops The downside of Linux when it comes to laptops is that it&amp;rsquo;s very power hungry, however we can fix this by installing a power saving program called auto-cpufreq.
How to install auto-cpufreq There are many ways of installing auto-cpufreq provided at https://github.com/AdnanHodzic/auto-cpufreq.
However, I will install it from source code, since this way will work on most Linux distributions.
 Clone the git repository:  git clone https://github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rust Ownership</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/rust-ownership/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 15:44:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/rust-ownership/</guid>
      <description>Understanding Ownership Ownership is what enables Rust to make memory safety guarantees without needing a garbage collector.
What is a Garbage collector? Garbage collection (GC) is a form of automatic memory management.
It attempts to reclaim memory which was allocated by the program, but is no longer used &amp;mdash; hence the name garbage.
GC exists to relieve the programmer from manually managing memory, which can be susceptible to errors such as memory leaks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pop!_OS Install</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/popos-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 19:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/popos-install/</guid>
      <description>Pop!_OS is a free and open-source Linux distribution, based on Ubuntu, and it uses the GNOME desktop.
It provides full support for AMD and Nvidia graphics cards out-of-the-box, which makes it an excellent choice for beginners.
Download Pop!_OS Go to https://pop.system76.com/ and click on download.
Pop!_OS comes in two versions: the latest, and the LTS (Long Term Support). I will choose the latest, since I want to use the latest features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disable Suspend on Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/disable-suspend/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 13:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/disable-suspend/</guid>
      <description>Disable / Mask services using systemctl sudo systemctl mask sleep.target suspend.target hibernate.target hybrid-sleep.target Edit &amp;ldquo;/etc/systemd/logind.conf&amp;rdquo; to avoid errors and high CPU usage HandleSuspendKey=ignore HandleHibernateKey=ignore HandleLidSwitch=ignore HandleLidSwitchExternalPower=ignore HandleLidSwitchDocked=ignore Restart systemd-logind sudo systemctl restart systemd-logind Check for errors journalctl -xe That&amp;rsquo;s it!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
