<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on jpnt website</title>
    <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on jpnt website</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© João Pinto</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jpnt.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Linux Audio Guide</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/linux-audio-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/linux-audio-guide/</guid>
      <description>Linux Audio Guide Compared to other OSes, Linux can leave much to be desired when it comes to audio quality, because most of the time Linux just uses generic open-source drivers to handle audio, which may not be optimized for every device. However with a few tweaks, it is possible to significantly improve the sound quality.&#xA;PipeWire vs PulseAudio PipeWire aims to replace both PulseAudio and JACK by providing a unified solution for audio and video handling.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>inici(os)</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/inicios/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/inicios/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: The Problem The growing complexity and size of modern software is a significant issue, which I have discussed previously here.&#xA;Today, software tends to be bloated, with enormous and complex codebases that can consist of tens of millions of lines of code and intricate dependency trees, often just to perform simple tasks.&#xA;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t always like this. In the past, when computers had limited processing power, developers had less freedom and were compelled to solve problems in more efficient ways.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trees</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/trees/</guid>
      <description>A tree is a hierarchical data structure composed of nodes connected by edges. The structure starts with a single root node and extends downwards, forming parent-child relationships among nodes. Each node, except the root, has exactly one parent, and nodes with no children are called leaf nodes. Various concepts and properties characterize trees.&#xA;Concepts Nodes and Edges&#xA;Node: Basic unit in a tree that contains data and may have zero or more child nodes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tweaking TLP</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/tweaking-tlp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 18:30:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/tweaking-tlp/</guid>
      <description>Problem Linux battery life on laptops is known to not be great; If you are a student or travel frequently you will want that your machine lasts some time.&#xA;Solution There are many things one can do to improve battery life:&#xA;Lower screen brightness Turn off keyboard backlight Turn off Bluetooth Turn off Wifi Use resource efficient software Use the appropriate drivers for your system But I am going to focus on TLP, a power management tool which will allow us to optimize the battery usage on Linux.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Docker to Podman</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/docker-to-podman/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 23:30:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/docker-to-podman/</guid>
      <description>Motivation Containerization has become a common practise of modern software development; Docker has been a popular choice for container orchestration, however, as the field evolves, new tools emerge.&#xA;One of those is Podman; one of the premises of it is that it does not require a daemon, unlike docker (dockerd).&#xA;This is one of the many more reasons people are starting to migrate to podman.&#xA;For more information I recommend reading: https://docs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iproute2</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/iproute2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 19:09:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/iproute2/</guid>
      <description>iproute2 is the Linux networking toolkit that replaced net-tools (ifconfig, route, arp etc.).&#xA;This post serves mostly to compare the old commands with the new standard ones. If you want a more detailed cheatsheet I encourage you to visit https://paulgorman.org/technical/linux-iproute2-cheatsheet.html&#xA;net-tools vs iproute2 table Net-tools Command iproute2 Command Description ifconfig ip addr Show or manipulate network interfaces route ip route Display or manipulate the IP routing table arp ip neigh or ip -4 neigh Show or manipulate the ARP cache netstat ss or ip -s Display network connections, routing tables, interface statistics, masquerade connections, and multicast memberships hostname hostnamectl Query and change the system hostname and related settings dnsdomainname hostnamectl --transient Query and change the system transient hostname and related settings domainname hostnamectl --static Query and change the system static hostname and related settings nisdomainname hostnamectl --pretty Query and change the system pretty hostname and related settings ifconfig -a ip addr show Show information about all network interfaces, including those that are down route -n ip route show Display the routing table in numeric format ifconfig &amp;lt;iface&amp;gt; up/down ip link set &amp;lt;iface&amp;gt; up/down Bring an interface up or down arp -s &amp;lt;ip&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mac&amp;gt; ip neigh add &amp;lt;ip&amp;gt; lladdr &amp;lt;mac&amp;gt; Add a static ARP entry netstat -tuln ss -tuln Display listening sockets for TCP and UDP netstat -rn ip route show Display the routing table Why iproute2?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Databases</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/databases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 16:47:56 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/databases/</guid>
      <description>Introductory Concepts A database (DB) is defined as a collection of related data; A database management system (DBMS) is the software that manages and controls access to the DB.&#xA;A database application is a program which interacts with the database at some point in its execution; Database system is a term used for a collection of application programs that interact with the DB along with the DBMS.&#xA;File-Based systems Before the database system there was the file-based system which is now obsolete.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pointers</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/pointers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/pointers/</guid>
      <description>What are pointers? In programming, a pointer is a derived data type (like arrays, structs and unions).&#xA;Instead of storing values like normal types, pointers store memory addresses of another data objects. Hence the name pointer, because these addresses &amp;ldquo;point&amp;rdquo; to some data.&#xA;In short, a pointer is: a variable that contains a memory address (as its value).&#xA;We will see how they prove to be very useful and how to use them in the C programming language.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steam on Void Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/voidlinux-steam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 23:21:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/voidlinux-steam/</guid>
      <description>How to install Steam on Void Linux 1. Non-free repositories To install Steam, you will need to enable the non-free repositories. To do so, install the non-free repository packages:&#xA;# xbps-install -S void-repo-nonfree void-repo-multilib-nonfree 2. Install Steam Now, you should have the Steam package available. To install it:&#xA;# xbps-install -S steam 3. Additional packages Unlike the Arch Linux steam package, in Void Linux this package does not contain the additional library packages.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Native</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/cloud-native/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 22:06:11 -0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/cloud-native/</guid>
      <description>Cloud Native is a Modern Software approach that makes use of cloud computing to build and execute scalable programs.&#xA;The goal of Cloud Native development Speed of software development.&#xA;The concepts of Cloud Native Cloud Native development is divided into four aspects:&#xA;DevOps&#xA;Manage infrastructure as code Merge Developers and Operators Continuous integration/Continuous development (CI/CD)&#xA;Always shipping software Automation of testing software Microservices&#xA;Scaling of application components Communication between components via APIs Containers</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Take Notes in VIM</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/vimwiki/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 20:26:06 -0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/vimwiki/</guid>
      <description>There are a lot of programs to take notes on, however, if you use VIM, why not take notes on your own text editor?&#xA;Install a plugin manager Make sure you have some type of VIM plugin manager installed. Personally, I use ´vim-plug´.&#xA;Install ´vim-plug´ for VIM, on Unix based systems:&#xA;curl -fLo ~/.vim/autoload/plug.vim --create-dirs \ https://raw.githubusercontent.com/junegunn/vim-plug/master/plug.vim Documentation is available at: https://github.com/junegunn/vim-plug&#xA;Install vimwiki Edit ´~/.vimrc´ to configure VIM and make it use vimwiki:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSH Configuration</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/ssh-config/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 19:59:08 -0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/ssh-config/</guid>
      <description>SSH Daemon (sshd) Configuration File The SSH daemon settings can be entirely configured through its configuration file located at /etc/ssh/sshd_config. Use a text editor to modify it.&#xA;Recommended settings:&#xA;PermitRootLogin no PubkeyAuthentication yes AuthorizedKeysFile .ssh/authorized_keys PasswordAuthentication no How To Use SSH Keys The client creates a private key and sends a public key to the server.&#xA;Private &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Client&#xA;Public &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Server&#xA;Create key pair in client $ ssh-keygen -b 4096 Copy public key to server $ ssh-copy-id -i ~/.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Most People Fail to Get I.T.</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/why-most-people-fail-to-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 14:56:45 -0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/why-most-people-fail-to-get-it/</guid>
      <description>The Information Technology field is immensely vast, however, one can break it down in these core aspects.&#xA;What is IT? Programming Computer Networking Databases Operating Systems The problem The issue is that most people, even ones on the field, fail to grasp the core basics. They try to invent theories on what information technology is, and end up abstracting real problems with layers of garbage that just create new problems.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modern Software is a disaster</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/modern-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 21:02:39 -0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/modern-software/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Designing simple and elegant software is far more difficult than letting ad-hoc or over-ambitious features obscure the code over time.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; suckless.org&#xA;We live in a really agitated world where information flows much faster than anyone could ever grasp. Due to the agile technological advancements and the appearance of new technologies every day, the demand for people on the Information Technology sector is extremely high.&#xA;However, because there is still so much software to write, there is no market pressure in the software space to ship high quality code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEARN LINUX THE RIGHT WAY</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/learn-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 22:41:20 -0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/learn-linux/</guid>
      <description>WHAT IS LINUX? Concept of a kernel Hardware &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Kernel &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Software Monolithic kernel vs Microkernel Open source nature Worldwide development You can contribute to it WHAT IS A LINUX DISTRIBUTION OS based on monolithic Linux kernel WHAT MAKES A LINUX DISTRIBUTION Core: libc; Base: coreutils; Extras; Most Linux distros differ on Extras DIFFERENCE BETWEEN LINUX DISTROS User-friendly vs user-centric distros Rolling release vs fixed release Linux Mint vs Arch Binary vs Source based INSTALLING SOFTWARE ON A LINUX DISTRO A linux distro distributes packages Package manager: apt, pacman ´apt install firefox´ ´pacman -S firefox´ FLEXIBILITY OF LINUX Used on super computers 100% of top 500 Used on the server 96% of top 1,000,000 Used on personal computers INTRODUCTION TO THE TERMINAL Commands are programs ls, cd, cat, pwd, whoami, echo, ps Learn every command: ´man command´ Everything is a file Programs, devices and drivers are files ´ls /dev´, ´ls /bin´ AUTOMATION AND SCRIPTING Bash scripts Shell vs Terminal Variables: PATH, export, env ´#!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Save Battery on Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/battery-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 18:52:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/battery-linux/</guid>
      <description>Linux on laptops The downside of Linux when it comes to laptops is that it&amp;rsquo;s very power hungry, however we can fix this by installing a power saving program called auto-cpufreq.&#xA;How to install auto-cpufreq There are many ways of installing auto-cpufreq provided at https://github.com/AdnanHodzic/auto-cpufreq.&#xA;However, I will install it from source code, since this way will work on most Linux distributions.&#xA;Clone the git repository: $ git clone https://github.com/AdnanHodzic/auto-cpufreq.git Change the directory to the repository and execute the installer: $ cd auto-cpufreq &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rust Ownership</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/rust-ownership/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 15:44:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/rust-ownership/</guid>
      <description>Understanding Ownership Ownership is what enables Rust to make memory safety guarantees without needing a garbage collector.&#xA;What is a Garbage collector? Garbage collection (GC) is a form of automatic memory management.&#xA;It attempts to reclaim memory which was allocated by the program, but is no longer used &amp;mdash; hence the name garbage.&#xA;GC exists to relieve the programmer from manually managing memory, which can be susceptible to errors such as memory leaks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pop!_OS Install</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/popos-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 19:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/popos-install/</guid>
      <description>Pop!_OS is a free and open-source Linux distribution, based on Ubuntu, and it uses the GNOME desktop.&#xA;It provides full support for AMD and Nvidia graphics cards out-of-the-box, which makes it an excellent choice for beginners.&#xA;Download Pop!_OS Go to https://pop.system76.com/ and click on download.&#xA;Pop!_OS comes in two versions: the latest, and the LTS (Long Term Support). I will choose the latest, since I want to use the latest features.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disable Suspend on Linux</title>
      <link>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/disable-suspend/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 13:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jpnt.github.io/posts/disable-suspend/</guid>
      <description>Disable / Mask services using systemctl sudo systemctl mask sleep.target suspend.target hibernate.target hybrid-sleep.target Edit &amp;ldquo;/etc/systemd/logind.conf&amp;rdquo; to avoid errors and high CPU usage HandleSuspendKey=ignore HandleHibernateKey=ignore HandleLidSwitch=ignore HandleLidSwitchExternalPower=ignore HandleLidSwitchDocked=ignore Restart systemd-logind sudo systemctl restart systemd-logind Check for errors journalctl -xe That&amp;rsquo;s it!</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
